Lowell Thomas Jr. Audio Tape Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Lowell Thomas Jr. Audio Tape Collection
1950 1973
62 Audio Tapes
The Lowell Thomas Jr Audio Tape Collection contains sixty-two reel-to-reel audio tapes recorded by Lowell Thomas Jr. These recordings include soundtracks and backgrond sound effects for films, and speeches from family gatherings.
Marist College Archives and Special Collections James A. Cannavino Library, First Floor, Room 134 3399 North Road Poughkeepsie New York 12601 United States
There are no restrictions on this collection
Lowell Thomas Jr. was born on 6 October 1923 in London, England, to Lowell Jackson Thomas (1892-1981) and Frances Ryan Thomas (1893-1975). His early childhood was spent in New York City due to his father’s work broadcasting a nightly radio news show. He and his parents would spend weekends at the family home in Quaker Hill.
After graduating from Taft School in 1942, Lowell Thomas Jr. went to Dartmouth College before his studies were interrupted by World War II and he enlisted in the United States Army Air Corps. Before he could see combat, he suffered from an illness and, instead, became a flight instructor during the war. Following the war, he returned to Dartmouth and graduated in the class of 1946. Lowell Thomas Jr. developed passions for flying and skiing that he would continue for the rest of his life. After graduation, he traveled to Iran and Turkey, where he collected materials for travelogues that he presented on a U.S. tour during the winter of 1948-49.
In 1949, he and his father, Lowell Thomas Sr., the renowned broadcaster, writer, and world traveler became two of the few Westerners allowed entry into Tibet. The responsibility for filming, photographing, and tape recording the sights and sounds of Tibetan life fell mostly to Lowell Thomas Jr. During the journey back out of Tibet, his father was thrown from his horse shattering his hip. The rough, narrow roads to and from Tibet would not allow the passage of automobiles and with little medical supplies, Lowell Thomas Jr. created a makeshift stretcher for his father. Lowell Thomas Jr. wrote the bestselling book, Out of This World, and later produced a documentary of the same name. In 2005, the Dalai Lama referred to him as “one of the genuine grandfathers of the Tibet movement in America” and bestowed upon him the International Campaign for Tibet’s Light of Truth Award.
Following his return from Tibet, Lowell Thomas Jr. married Mary “Tay” Pryor. They were married for 64 years until her death in 2014. In 1954, he and Tay bought a Cessna 180 in which they traveled much of the globe while documenting their travels. They would publish articles on their trip and co-wrote the book, Our Flight to Adventure.
In 1958, they flew to Alaska with their toddler Anne and fell in love with the territory. Two years later, they would relocate there and would remain residents of Alaska for the rest of their lives.
Soon after moving to Anchorage, Lowell Thomas Jr. began his many years of public service. After unsuccessfully running twice for the U.S. House, he ran for state Senate. From 1967 to 1974, Lowell Thomas Jr. represented the Alaska Senate from District E as a Republican.
Thomas also became deeply involved in conservation issues. Some of his notable contributions were his work against the bounty hunting of wolves and work that led to the establishment of Chugach State Park in 1970.
In 1974, Lowell Thomas Jr. was elected as Alaska’s third lieutenant governor under Governor Jay Hammond. However, a controversy arose after remarks Thomas made were interpreted as approving of apartheid in South Africa. Hammond backed Thomas, calling it a hypocritical smear, but accepted his decision not to seek a second term.
Following his time in office, Lowell Thomas Jr. bought Talkeetna Air Taxi Service in 1981, an Alaskan bush pilot service, and remained an active pilot into his 80s. He shuttled skiers in the Alaska Range and onto North America’s tallest peak, Denali in his Helio Courier. Lowell Thomas Jr. has logged over 10,000 hours in the air without ever scratching a plane. In 2012, Lowell Thomas Jr. was inducted into the Aviation Museum Hall of Fame to which he also donated his beloved Helio Courier.
Lowell Thomas Jr. devoted much of his time and money to conservation issues and public service, and he and Tay aided many charitable causes. Among the many organizations the Thomases supported were the Alaska Conservation Foundation, the National Parks, and the Conservation Association. He helped to create the Thomas Planetarium at the Anchorage Museum, the Thomas Training Center on Eagle Glacier near Girdwood, and the Thomas Center for Senior Living at St. Mary’s Episcopal Church. Lowell Thomas Jr. was awarded a lifetime achievement award by the National Parks Conservation Association in 1995 and awarded the William Penn Mott Jr. Leadership Award by the Alaska Conservation Foundation in 2004. In 2011, the Alaska Conservation Foundation established the Lowell Thomas, Jr. Award for outstanding achievement by an Alaskan-based organization or program.
Lowell Thomas Jr. wrote several books, including Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet, The Silent War in Tibet, and Our Flight to Adventure. On 1 October 2016, Lowell Thomas Jr., aged 92, died.
This collection consists of reel-to-reel audio tapes recorded by Lowell Thomas Jr.
Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981; Thomas, Lowell, 1923-2016
This collection is organized into five series: 1. Flight to Adventure, 2. Lowell Thomas Senior, 3. Tibet, 4. Thornburg Party, 5. Miscellany
No accruals are expected.
[Lowell Thomas Jr. Papers](https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_5433)
[Lowell Thomas Film Collection](https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_3699)
[Lowell Thomas Memorabilia Collection](https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_224_114)
[Lowell Thomas Papers: Graphic Materials](https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_227_262)
[Lowell Thomas Papers: Objects](https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_225_122)
[Lowell Thomas Papers: Sound Recordings](https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_227_251)
[Lowell Thomas Papers: Textual Materials](https://www.empireadc.org/search/catalog/npkmc_225_061)
- 1. Flight to Adventure, 1954-1964; 20 tapes
  - Narration by Lowell Thomas Jr., 1954-1955 (Tape 1)
  - Morocco music and effects reel 2, 1954-1955 (Tape 2)
  - Timbuktu commentary part #2 by Lowell Thomas, February 1964 (Tape 3)
  - Lecture music and effects reel 1, 1955 (Tape 4)
  - Lecture music and effects reel 2, 1955 (Tape 5)
  - Various recordings, 1954-1955 (Tape 6)
  - Congo, native dance at Paulis, May 2, 1954 (Tape 7)
  - Flight to Adventure; sounds of dancers and administration meeting, 1954 (Tape 8)
  - Sound effects for pygmey sequence, 1954-1955 (Tape 9)
  - Additional pygmy sound effects, 1954-1955 (Tape 10)
  - Pygmy and Watusi music for TV recording, 1954-1955 (Tape 11)
  - TV Advertisement with Lowell Thomas, 1954-1955 (Tape 12)
  - Various sound effects; Reel 1-A, 1954-1955 (Tape 13)
  - Accompanying music, 1954-1955 (Tape 14)
  - various sound effects (1), 1954-1955 (Tape 15)
  - various sound effects (2), 1954-1955 (Tape 16)
  - various sound effects (3), December 1954 - January 1955 (Tape 17)
  - Sinbad music and effects, 1954-1955 (Tape 18)
  - Lecture sound effects, 1954-1955 (Tape 19)
  - Reel 2-B, 1954-1955 (Tape 20)
- 2. Lowell Thomas Senior, 1963-1966; 5 tapes
  - Address at Macalester College, September 22, 1966 (Tape 21)
  - Radio "bloopers", undated (Tape 22)
  - Salt Lake City recording, March 15, 1963 (Tape 23)
  - Labor Talk on TV, undated (Tape 24)
  - Message to school age boys and girls, undated (Tape 25)
- 3. Tibet, 1950-1972; 11 tapes
  - Tibet LT Jr voice track; production #353, reel #1, circa 1950 (Tape 26)
  - Tibet LT Jr voice track; production #353, reel #2, circa 1950 (Tape 27)
  - Tibet LT Jr voice track; production #353, reel #3, circa 1950 (Tape 28)
  - Tibet LT Jr voice track; production #353, reel #4, circa 1950 (Tape 29)
  - Tibet Reel 1 (1960-61 print) track ½, 1960-1961 (Tape 30)
  - Tibet Reel 2 (1966 print, redone 1972) (Tape 31)
  - Tibet Reel 1B and 2A; old version, 1959 (Tape 32)
  - Tibet music 1-A, circa 1950 (Tape 33)
  - Tibet Reel 2 “B” old version, 1959 (Tape 34)
  - Talk with the Dalai Lama and John Fabor; duplicate recording for radio, 1964 (Tape 35)
  - Tibet reel 1 (new), 1966 (Tape 36)
- 4. Thornburg Party, 1967; 6 tapes
  - Reel 1 edited copy, August 6, 1967 (Tape 37)
  - Reel 2 edited copy, August 6, 1967 (Tape 38)
  - Reel 3 edited copy, August 6, 1967 (Tape 39)
  - Reel 1, August 6, 1967 (Tape 40)
  - Reel 2, August 6, 1967 (Tape 41)
  - Reel 3, August 6, 1967 (Tape 42)
- 5. Miscellany, 1963-1973; 20 tapes
  - Kennedy NBC Program “The Highest Price” Reel 1, November 24, 1963 (Tape 43)
  - Kennedy NBC Program “The Highest Price” Reel 2, November 24, 1963 (Tape 44)
  - Morocco sound effects reel 1, undated (Tape 45)
  - Mr. World “Replogle” Globes, undated (Tape 46)
  - Untitled, 1965 (Tape 47)
  - Alexander, Herb; archaeology music tracks, undated (Tape 48)
  - Newhart, Bob; various recordings, January 17, 1964 (Tape 49)
  - Various recordings; Conrad – ski songs, Harrison Woods, undated (Tape 50)
  - Round the World Via the Poles, flight expedition, January 10, 1966 (Tape 51)
  - Recording of a monk singing at Sera, undated (Tape 52)
  - Reel 2 DSP, May 5, 1968 (Tape 53)
  - Recordings of Shackleston, Lindbergh; Peary; T. R. Roosevelt, March 1963 (Tape 54)
  - Destination South Pacific music part 1, intermission and playout music, undated (Tape 55)
  - “How to have a wonderful life” by Norman V. Peale, August 7, 1970 (Tape 56)
  - Captain Eddie Rickendecker memorial service, August 7, 1973 (Tape 57)
  - LT Jr. Reel 1, Flight over Both Poles, November 1965 (Tape 58)
  - LT and LT Jr Reel 2, Flight over Both Poles, November 1965 (Tape 59)
  - Mary Taylor Thomas on the $64,000 challenge, March 31, 1957 (Tape 60)
  - Max W. Thornburg Middle East Address Reel 1, 1953 (Tape 61)
  - Max W. Thornburg Middle East Address Reel 2 duplicate, 1953 (Tape 62)